<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Way of the Program on How to Think Like a Computer Scientist: Learning with Python 3 (Blue Ridge Boost Edition)</title>
    <link>https://blueridgeboost.com/pythonbook/chapter_01/</link>
    <description>Recent content in The Way of the Program on How to Think Like a Computer Scientist: Learning with Python 3 (Blue Ridge Boost Edition)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 11:30:50 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blueridgeboost.com/pythonbook/chapter_01/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Formal and natural languages</title>
      <link>https://blueridgeboost.com/pythonbook/chapter_01/s01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blueridgeboost.com/pythonbook/chapter_01/s01/</guid>
      <description>As noted in the introduction, this course teaches you how to think like a computer scientist. A crucial aspect of a computer scientist&amp;rsquo;s job is to communicate solutions to people and machines. We use two languages to communicate.
Natural and Formal Languages Natural languages are the languages that people speak, such as English, Spanish, and French. They were not designed by people (although people try to impose some order on them); they evolved naturally.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programs</title>
      <link>https://blueridgeboost.com/pythonbook/chapter_01/s02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blueridgeboost.com/pythonbook/chapter_01/s02/</guid>
      <description>A program is a sequence of instructions that specifies how to perform a computation. The computation might be something mathematical, such as solving a system of equations or finding the roots of a polynomial, but it can also be a symbolic computation, such as searching and replacing text in a document.
The details look different in different languages, but a few basic instructions appear in just about every language:
input. Get data from the keyboard, a file, or some other device.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
